Inventory of the Klaus Barbie pre-trial records
Hoover Institution Archives
Klaus Barbie pre-trial records
1943-1985
95008
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes (3.2 linear feet)
Trial instruction, including depositions and exhibits, in the case of Klaus Barbie before the Tribunal de grande instance de Lyon, relating to German war crimes in France during World War II. Photocopy.
Barbie, Klaus, 1913-, defendant.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1995.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Tribunal de grande instance, Lyon, France.
Biographical note
Born to a Roman Catholic family in Bad Godesberg, Germany, Klaus Barbie joined the SS (Schutzstaffel) in September 1935. By 1940, he was posted to Holland where his main task was to arrest Jews and German émigrés. In 1942, Barbie arrived in recently captured Lyon as head of the Gestapo, commanding a force of 25 officers. There, Barbie prevented sabotage and persecuted Jews, for which he was presented the military award, "First Class Iron Cross with Swords," by Adolf Hitler. After the war Barbie escaped prosecution in France and relocated to Bolivia in 1950. He lived in Bolivia as a businessman until 1983, when the Bolivian government extradited Barbie to France to stand trial for war crimes. In 1987 Klaus Barbie was sentenced to life imprisonment for crimes against humanity. Nine jurors and three judges found Barbie, known as the "Butcher of Lyon," guilty of the 341 separate charges that were brought against him at the court in Lyon. While in prison Klause Barbie died of cancer in 1991.
Scope and Content of Collection
The trial records for the head of the Gestapo in Lyon include trial instruction, depositions, and exhibits in the case of Klaus Barbie before the Tribunal de grande instance in Lyon, relating to German war crimes in France during World War II. Photocopy.
France. Tribunal de grande instance de Lyon.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); War crime trials--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Atrocities.
- Introductory indictment, October 9, 1981 (Text 1: 1)
- Verbal Trial, in French, May 28, 1984 (Text 1: 2)
- Verbal Trial, copies in German, November 1982 (Text 1: 3)
- Letter of instruction for the judge, March 17, 1983 (Text 1: 4)
- Final indictment, July 15, 1985 (Text 1: 5)
- Special hearing of Ferdinand Palk, December 1964 (Text 2: 1)
- Lischka, Hagen, and Heinrichsohn trial proceedings, February 1982
  Summary
  Kurt Lischka was the head of the Gestapo in Cologne in 1940, and in 1943 he became chief of the department overseeing internment camps and executions. In 1971, Serge Klarsfeld, a French/Jewish lawyer and holocaust survivor, found Lischka living in Cologne, West Germany and by the late 1970s he and his wife Beate were able to get him to trial. Herbert-Martin Hagen was a personal assistant to the SS police chief in France and head of a department in the Paris Gestapo, and Ernst Heinrichsohn worked in the Gestapo's Jewish affairs department in Paris. Both were integral parts of Lischka's work, and both were arrested in 1980. These records are the proceedings from the trial.
  - Indictment against Lischka, Hagen, and Heinrichsohn, February 1982 (Text 2: 2-4)
  - Judgment of the Lischka, Hagen, and Heinrichsohn case, in French and German, February 1982 (Text 3)
- Report to the U.S. Attorney General, August 1983 (Text 2: 5)
  Report to the Attorney General regarding the status of the investigations and proceedings in the Klaus Barbie trial.
- Rogatory letters, in French and German, 1982 - 1984 (Text 4 - 5, Text 6: 1)
  Rogatory Letters for evidence requests from the French to the Germans, as well as services of process from the Germans to the French with regards to the Klaus Barbie investigation.
- Gendarmerie Nationale witness hearings and statements, February 1983 - May 1984 (Text 6: 2-4)
  Interviews and hearings conducted by the national police force of France on witnesses involved in the Klaus Barbie investigation.
- Inventory record of proceedings against Klaus Barbie and Knob Werner, March 1981 (Text 7: 2)
- Information regarding the raid of the general union of Jews in France, December 1984 (Text 7: 3)
  Information regarding the Gestapo actions to hunt down French Jews in their streets and houses with intentions of sending them to concentration camps or extermination sites.
- Military intelligence summary of the investigation against Klaus Barbie, April 1980 (Text 7: 1)
- Final witness hearings and statements, 1985 (Text 7: 4)
- "Activities of Jewish Organisations in France During the Occupation", 1947 (Text 8: 1)
- "Les Fils et Filles des Deportes Juifs de France" and Serge Klarsfeld, 1943, 1946, 1981 (Text 8: 2)
  Serge Klarsfeld founded the association of "Sons and Daughters of Jewish Deportees from France" in 1979, consisting of descendants of French-Jews who endured concentration camps during World War II. These files contains publications written in conjunction with the organization.
- "Memorial of the Deportation of French Jews" by Serge Klarsfeld, 1978 (Text 8: 3)